Guide to the Georgii Grabbe Papers, ca. 1930-1995
Department of Special Collections
Georgii Grabbe Papers,
ca. 1930-1995
Special Collections M0964
Grabbe, Georgii.
2.75 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1998.
Biography
Metropolitan (Bishop) Grigorii, secular name Iurii Pavlovich Grabbbe (1902-1995) was head of the Russian Church Synod Abroad from 1950?-1995?
Scope and Content
Includes documents of the Synod, correspondence between various leaders of the Russian Orthodox Church Abroad, correspondence with other leaders of the Russian emigration, and his own lectures and writings.
Access Terms
Afanasii, Metropolitan.; Alekseev, Vasilii Ivanovich.; Anastasii, Metropolitan.; Antonii, Metropolitan.; Azkoul, Michael.; Chiliiskii, Leontii.; Dulgov, Serafim.; Filaret, Metropolitan.; Grigorii, Bishop.; Grabbe, Igumeniia Magdalina.; Khomiakova, Obshchestvo.; Kirilovich, Vladimir.; Kovalevskii, Leonid Iur'evich.; Krasovskii, Oleg Antonovich.; Lavr', Archbishop.; Lebedev, Lev.; Lozovoi, Vladimir Nikolaevich.; Rar, Gleb Aleksandrovich; Rodzianko, Vasilii.; Samarin, Vladimir Dmitrevich.; Sapozhkova, Ekaterina Arkad'evna.; Scvortzoff, Kos'ma.; Seide-Labalette, G.; Varnava, Bishop, 1887-1963.; Zernov, Nikolai N.; Russian Orthodox Church Abroad.; Russian Americans.
Container List
- First shipment:
  - Letters of Metropolitan Anastasii to Grabbe (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters of Grabbe to Anastasii Metropolitan Anastasii (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters of Metropolitan Antonii and Grabbe (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters of Metropolitan Filaret (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters of Grabbe to Metropolitan Afanasii (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters of Grabbe to Metropolitan Antonii (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters from Grabbe to Metropolitan Antonii (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Metropolitan Antonii (Lebed) documents (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Grabbe to Vasilii Ivanovich Alekseev (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence between Grabbe and Askul (Michael Azkoul) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Natanashev to Grabbe (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Vitalii to Grabbe (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Vitalii to Grabbe (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Petr Sergeevich Lopukhin to Grabbe (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Varia: letters to Anastazii, Grabbe to Filaret. Grabbe to Antonii and Antonii to Grabbe (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Second shipment (received 2 June 1998):
  - Various correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Various correspondence, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mikhal'chenkov et al. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Grabbe-Verditskkii, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bishop Grigorii (Grabbbe) writings about Bishop Varnava and "Varnava case" (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence Grabbe-Grotov, 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Grabbe letters to various addressees, 1948-1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Grabbe lectures, 1960-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Grabbe lectures, 1990-1995 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Accession, 1998-240
  (received 7/22/98)
  - Igumeniia Magdalina (sister of Grabbe), 1950-1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Igumeniia Magdalina, 1978-1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Nikolai N. Zernov, 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Mitrophan and documents pertaining to Mitrophan, 1950-1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Protoerei Lev Lebedev, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Archbishop Leontii Chiliiskii, 1949-1954 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Archbisop Lavr', 1967-1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Oleg Antonovich Krasovskii, 1989-1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Dr. Leonid Iur'evich Kovalevskii, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Rev. German Ivanovich Trinadtsatyi, 1979-1985 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Vladimir Nikolaevich Lozovoi, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Accession, 1998-269:
  - Velikii Kniaz' Vladimir Kirilovich and other important letters (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Khomiakov's society (Obshchestvo Khomiakova) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Dr. G. Seide-Labalette (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Kos'ma Scvortzoff (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Sarafim Archbishop of Chicago and Detroit (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with Bishop Serafim Dulgov (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Ekaterina Arkad'evna Sapozhkova (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Various letters, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with Vladimir Dmitrevich Samarin (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with Archbishop Paul of Australia and New Zealand (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with Archbishop Mark of Berlin and Germany and a few others (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with Gleb Aleksandrovich Rar of Publishing House Posev (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Bishop Vasilii Rodzianko (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Accession, 1999-117:
  - Off-prints of various writing and typescripts by the Most Rev. Grabbe (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Off-prints of various writing and typescripts by the Most Rev. Grabbe (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Off-prints of various writing and typescripts by the Most Rev. Grabbe (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Journal, "Rossiiskoe edinstvo" (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Grabbe correspondence with Grand Duchess (Kniaginiia) Leonida Georgievna Romanov and Russkaia Zarubezhnaia Ekspertnaia Komissiia/Russian Expert Commission Abroad, Stratford, CT (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Grabbe correspondence with Leonid Kovalevsky, Gelii Riabov, offprints, etc. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Grabbe correspondence with Grand Duke (Kniaz) Nikolai Romanovich (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Grand Duke (Kniaz) Vladimir Kiriilovich Romanov, covering years 1948-1994 (Box 8, Folder 4-7)
  - Correspondence between Most Reverend Grigorii Grabbe with Stefan K. [?], 1977-1986 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence between Most Rev. Grabbe with Stefan K[?], 1987-1990 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Clippings and various correspondence pertaining to Mr. Goleniewski, a pretender to be Aleksei Nikolaevich Romanov, the son of the last Czar of Russia. Some correspondence relates to the Most Rev. Grabbe's involvement in this affair, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Clippings and various correspondence pertaining to Mr. Goleniewski, a pretender to be Aleksei Nikolaevich Romanov, the son of the last Czar of Russia. Some correspondence relates to the Most Rev. Grabbe's involvement in this affair, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Clippings and various correspondence pertaining to Mr. Goleniewski, a pretender to be Aleksei Nikolaevich Romanov, the son of the last Czar of Russia. Some correspondence relates to the Most Rev. Grabbe's involvement in this affair, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Publications regarding the Imperial family (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and clippings pertaining to the Goleniewski affair and covering periods 1964-1967 and 1968-1988 respectively (Box 11, Folder 1-10)
  - Nikolai Pavlovich Ghurilov (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Protoierei Aleksandr Trubnikov (Troubnikoff) (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Rev. Igor Troianov (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Underground Church under communism (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - First Great Synod of Eastern Orthodoxy and some other materials, 1968-1978 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Various writings and documents primarily writings by Protoierei Viktor Potapov and Synod of Bishops of the Russian Orthodox Church Abroad including its press releases (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous letters, documents and offprints (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Sokol'skii, V. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous letters, documents and offprints (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous letters, documents and offprints (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Holy Synod of the Russian Orthodox Church Abroad and various letters and copies by Most Rev. Bishop Georgii Grabbe (Box 13, Folder 1-7)
  - Journal published by the Free Russian Orthodox Church in Russia (incomplete), 1991-1998 (Box 14)
  - Volume 1 of Bishop Georgii Grabbe works, 1964. (Box 14)